anyone who talks to me about becoming a
product manager I say well yeah I like
make a product like you can you can do
it today it doesn't have to be an iPhone
it doesn't have to be a you know it
could be a book to be a PDF even if it's
not you know the most perfect product or
offering but just the fact that they
said I'm gonna do this and ship it these
get to that like just ship an attitude
that is so essential what's up everyone
Matthew and Sina here and today we are
talking about the role of a product
manager what it is and the qualities you
need to succeed in this emerging
industry this conversation on product
management is brought to you by air
table millions of people use air table
to build their own software with use
cases ranging from cattle farming to
major video productions so I want to say
thank you to air table and we will get
into the conversation so who do we have
on today's show today we have Justin
zaccardi he's a product manager over at
tonal also joining us in the booth today
is Mark Contreras he's our in-house
editor and producer here at the future
and former employee at Google so I
decided to bring mark in so that he can
help add a little bit of color to the
conversation so let's start and go ahead
and welcome our guest Justin to the show
[Applause]
there's a whole three of us clapping for
you we try to make as much noise as
possible so for our audience who doesn't
know you yet if you want to give a brief
background as to who you are and maybe
why you're here on the show today yeah
well I like to mention I'm currently
leading product management for hardware
and software at a cool startup in San
Francisco called tonal we create and now
sell what we think is the world's most
intelligent fitness machine it's a home
gym and a personal trainer and all goes
on your wall so it's we're really
excited about trading that but you know
I've been in the product management role
my most of my career which is almost
about 15 years now and I've worked at
small startups medium-sized companies
and kind of big fortune 100 companies
like American Express in AT&T all in
that product management role so I've
really seen
seen the product manager job across
across industries and company sizes wow
that's fantastic that's we're very lucky
to have you then cuz I mean you've been
doing this for a long time and I think
the role of product manager even as a
title is I guess relatively new with a
lot of the emerging tech companies and
seeing all the new job listings out
there I feel like I have heard of it
more and more recently so for those of
us who don't know specifically me what
is a product manager do if you ask any
product manager the famous answer is
well it depends so I usually talk about
product management in almost like two
different ways that kind of balanced at
the same time one is just like a
definition and then one is almost like
with a metaphor or an allegory so you
know the the definition of product
management in my mind is it's a role
that is attempting to balance at all
times
balance the customer the business and
some sort of technology and to ensure
that you know there the company is
delivering some sort of value so the
product manager is essentially
responsible for value and delivering
value to either to the customer or in a
way that delivers value to the business
the three fundamentals of product
management are ensuring that products
are usable which is kind of like you
know customer focus are designed
valuable which is business focused and
then feasible which is like technology
doesn't it's possible to create or its
profitable to create the metaphor I like
to use is like a conductor of a symphony
and so the product manager isn't
developing the music but they're
ensuring that the music is played at the
symphony at the right balance and in the
right mix how do you as a product
manager help inform the creative side of
what's going to be impactful for the
business because earlier you were saying
it is a balance of making something an
amazing experience a beautiful
experience versus something that's going
to be profitable and good for the
business internally so how do you how do
you help bridge the gap for somebody who
might not have that information on the
creative side well the product manager
really needs to be responsible and be
able to articulate the why
why we're doing something and therefore
and be able to translate why into what
that makes so you know if the product
manager can hold on to that why and the
kind of the vision of what this thing
needs to be with the sound what the song
needs to feel like at the end you know
they're able to help prioritize and
order the right things to do to get to
get to that why mm-hmm I had a question
so a lot of our audience might have some
ideas of what a product manager does in
maybe like a physical product I know
that you're maybe more focused on
software so I guess what's the kind of
difference there when it comes to
software versus like a physical product
that's like yeah that's a great question
I'm looking this a lot at a in the
current current job because we are now
work on both hardware and software at
the same time what have found in you
know especially if you go anywhere
online you read about software they say
you know your cycle times are so short
it's so cheap to create new things and
try new things and experiment you can
always republish it it's easy to do
harder to do and you've just spent you
know thousands of dollars on a on a
template and talked to a guy in China
who's you know whose company's going to
build a tool that wants to build your
part that will go into a piece of
hardware so it's very expensive and it
takes a lot of time so you really need
to be right when you get to that stage
the common product manager today is all
about creating a hypothesis and creating
a test or an experiment that will allow
a team to to build confidence in that
what they're building is valuable for
their customer one of the big things
that a good product manager can do is
they can distill out of all of these
features and all of these ideas what are
what is the big benefit that you know
this this thing might might offer turns
out you don't need all the bells and
whistles in order to to deliver that
what that one little thing so that's you
know that's the idea of the MVP right
wasn't the product and if you can you
know um there's a minimal Viable Product
world and hardware as well as in
software or at a startup or at a big
company that clarifies it a lot because
I think there is
even some confusion on my part because
I've managed the small product when I
was working at Google but there were
some differences in how you would manage
it from a large scale to a small scale
especially you know which software so
that really clarifies nice press and it
changes things you know if it's a big
company or a small company if you have
millions of users or zero users you
actually do very different you can do
very you might have different tactics
but the principles are the same
you know I really love this conductor
analogy because it illustrates the
challenges and the art of guiding
everyone on a project towards a singular
goal I know many of you at home are
creatives and I think we can sometimes
get so focused on making our work
beautiful that we lose sight of the
bigger picture and the possible impact
for our business or the businesses of
our clients in this next portion Justin
walks us through how he deals with that
disconnection by bridging the gap
between the designers the engineers and
the stakeholders of a project sometimes
we joke around in various companies that
worked out we don't joke around that the
product managers their job is to go to
meetings so that designers and engineers
don't have to make and if you've ever
worked in some of these bigger companies
you know that it's just but I think that
gets to your question that says you know
the product manager is constantly like a
conduit for information to and from the
execution team and various stakeholders
and customers and that's again that that
nexus idea of that usable valuable
feasible so I work to a used to work at
American Express and led the mobile apps
so I could change in the mobile app to
how you might activate your credit card
there's a hole at a card activation
division that is gonna want to know
about the changes that were making or
customer service may have input
I guess there's like almost two
different layers of the people you work
with the first order is that core
execution team your designer your
engineering team and they're the folks
that are coming up with solutions to
certain problems the second layer of
some people call them like the
stakeholders where
you know they want to be almost informed
or connected to or you know have input
to the process but they're not going to
know how many steps of flow might need
to have or what color the button should
be right so for the stakeholders you're
just trying to stay high level with them
you're not trying to get into the weeds
you're just trying to give them bigger
chunks of updates rather than all the
nitty-gritty of how it works you know
say you launched a great product and you
have a customer service team who handles
a bunch of questions about the product
you know 20% of their phone calls that
they take are asking about this one
feature that doesn't seem to be working
exactly the right way that's a huge
opportunity for product management to
say there's a problem with this feature
bring that to design and say here's a
problem and then and then someone on the
design team might say oh my gosh this is
such an easy fix all I have to do is you
know reorder these two pages or these
two steps in the flow and I think we
could design around this issue this
confusing issue for our customers I
really like what you said about needing
the ability to distill information
because it's almost like you're speaking
a different language to the different
stakeholders so upper management might
need to hear it in more of a business
sense whereas when you're talking to the
technologists or the designers that's a
whole different language and you as a
p.m. is able to you're able to translate
what those needs are from top to bottom
yeah yeah that's a great point you'll
see you'll see in a lot of just like
articles or description of the product
management or even in job postings how
diplomacy and communication and
translation is such a an essential part
of the job and it's and it's funny I
think like no matter where you're on
your career in product management that
is an essential piece it's just the
people that you're translating to are to
and from might change with the high rate
of businesses being disrupted nowadays I
think it's important to know when you
should be iterating and when you should
be innovating I asked Justin how he
figures out when to iterate and when to
innovate when he has so many tasks and
options to juggle you know one of the
one of the frameworks or kind of tools
and the product manager toolbox is this
idea of jobs to be done
the idea is that people hire certain
products jobs for them in their life
one example is you know do you actually
when you buy a drill what are you really
buying you're buying a whole I'm
actually buying a drill
what a good product manager will do is
always have the jobs to be done in their
mind does the current product solve that
job effectively or is there is this time
to just rethink the whole thing can you
solve them so anyway the guy who
invented jobs to done is this Harvard
Business professor Clayton Christensen
the milkshake manifesto this innovation
consulting group was hired by one of the
fast-food chains to come up with a
better milkshake so that was the idea
they wanted to iterate on a milkshake so
these guys did a bunch of customer
research they started showing up the
fast-food chain they found that a bunch
of people were buying milkshakes
as something to do on their commute as a
way to kind of keep them almost
entertained as they drove to work in the
morning there's a whole fun story and
it's really worth seeing but at the end
of the day they said the job we can
innovate based on that job and the
breakfast smoothie was kind of invented
from that the milkshake manifesto really
convinced me that if you really focus on
like what is the hole that you're
providing you know not the drill but the
hole right you're you're able to you
know innovation Spurs from from that
type of focus you know there's a there's
another concept that kind of a an old
boss taught that is called the adjacent
possible
it's the uber for blank okay okay yeah
Eileen I get that the concept you know
if you're looking to kind of bring kind
of start with innovate innovative ideas
especially in the product sense it does
some of it does come from what's
happening in adjacent or related
industries right so that's that's a good
tip or anyone who's looking to make
innovation in their own company
organization or business they might look
at those adjacent opportunities or other
businesses and just dig in and see well
if we want to do this I'm sure somebody
else has done this very well so far
we've covered that good product managers
are able to communicate and translate
goals to many different groups
as well as help those groups see
problems in a different way in order to
spur innovation next Justin shares
additional qualities that help make a
product manager successful and tells us
how to get into product management I
always call these like the PM super
powers absolutely one person might have
two or three that they're really good at
or maybe one or two but if you build a
good product management team you'll have
all of these superpowers like on the on
the actual team but there's a there's a
sense of curiosity hmm and understanding
why that that is I think essential for a
great product manager you know people
will ask you for a B and C and maybe the
answer is green and and you have to you
have to understand what their
motivations are as part of that jobs to
be done thing or mm-hmm I think there's
another one that's just you know a
multi-disciplinarian like you have to
kind of know how things are made you
have to know find and built and the how
it's made is important when when your
job is to assess is the benefit worth
the cost
and make those kind of micro decisions
one is around like vision and intuition
maybe innovation they can see around a
corner they can see like five years
ahead you know that person might be able
to really help you know the rest of the
company point like you say towards a
towards something new and then I think
the one I think you mentioned this and
the skills you you reference but there's
just something about like getting stuff
done you know good product manager can
point to something and just and make
sure that that thing gets it shipped and
so the one thing I think product
managers need to be measured on is are
their ability to ship things to get out
there to deliver value and we talked
about tools a little bit is that you
know would you sum up the use of tools
being a a big part of that
organizational skill oh man the
day-to-day work of a product manager is
in spreadsheets in documents in you know
JIRA air table Google Docs like note
cards it's collecting all of these
things and sorting them prioritizing
them to make
that you know no good idea is left
behind but also that there is a only the
most important things are being worked
on by the team and so the organization
is really important
most most modern teams these days are
doing like an agile development and so
having a roadmap and a backlog are you
know and these are essentially long
lists of things to do and work on in a
certain order and so you know like you
mentioned air table we like I use air
table a lot to just collect all of my
ideas and sort them based on different
types of criteria so you know here's a
list of things that only I can work on
and here's a list of things that are
finished and like here's a list of
things that are not started yet and then
of course you need to be able to
communicate those things to others you
know in any day I'm probably creating a
spreadsheet pulling something out of air
table putting it into a slide deck
drawing up like fake wireframes or
mock-ups right like within the span of
four hours so it sounds like you're
getting the raw data you're organizing
it in a thoughtful way and then you're
preparing it in a way that you can
present it the idea to somebody so that
they can look at that and understand all
of the the matrix code that you were
just looking at yeah well thank you for
that's a very kind of way of putting it
a very glamorous way for those people
who are interested in product management
how might we get into product management
like what are their classes for this can
you get a degree in this like where how
do we become a product manager yeah I
you know what I I do not believe there
is a degree in product management I wish
there were yeah I have three pieces of
advice for someone who wants to be a
product manager the first is you know
understand what the the role and the the
responsibilities are and that's
something that's easy to do today you
can listen to podcast like this or you
can read some articles read some some
blog posts I think hacker noon on on
medium has some really great articles on
what product management is and what the
skills are that I think the best way to
to actually see if you
product management or even to to start
to develop your resume so that you can
get a job as a product manager is to
actually ship something this is like
something I try and talk to every anyone
who talks to me about becoming a product
manager I say well yeah I like make a
product like you can you can do it today
it doesn't have to be an iPhone it
doesn't have to be a you know it could
be a book it could be a PDF could be a
spreadsheet it could be I just found it
like I was looking on product hunt the
other day I found like literally an air
table spreadsheet that someone had
created that was a list of jobs for
Community Managers mm-hm
you know I'm sure they they they asked
people to pay them money to put it on
the spreadsheet and then they you know
got people to come to the webpage and
they're creating value for people
looking for jobs and for people who have
jobs no skills require just the the
foresight to to create value for two
different people there's nothing
stopping you like go out and try and
find something to make and and build it
and ship it mm-hmm
I love that because I think for me
especially when I hear that like if you
were to tell me like nothing's stopping
you from shipping a product that sounds
so intimidating so when I heard that at
first it's like that's that's pretty
intimidating myself that's a lot of work
but when you kind of boil it down to
just look for a problem and solve that
and deliver value to somebody and that
could be as small as bringing
information together in a PDF or a
spreadsheet that's enough to show that
you could take a problem that you see
and come up with a solution and then
deliver that to the intended community
so since you are hiring and you are
looking for people and like these things
stand out do you have any examples of
something that has stood out to you or
somebody had made one of these smaller
products that they've shipped and that
caught your attention like the one that
I mentioned I think is a kind of my
perfect example I've talked to people
who had we've had like maybe their own
company or they bootstrap something all
the way down to tutoring children but
when they can show that they distilled
their message or they're offering down
to it you know it a two paragraph
website with a domain and that they like
put themselves out there I feel like
that's even that's even valuable even if
it's not
you know the most perfect product or
offering but just the fact that they
said I'm gonna do this and ship it is
get to that like just ship it attitude
that is so essential that says a lot
about you know about someone's ability
to to do what it takes to be a really
good product product manager yeah it
sounds like the key thing now that I'm
starting to pick up is on all of these
examples that you gave there's a sense
of resourceful nested there right
somebody who's a good product manager or
shares the qualities of a good product
manager is somebody who's very
resourceful they know what they want to
do or what they can share or what what
they would like to convey or add value
to a community or an audience and they
just find whatever means necessary in
order to deliver that value whether that
is a website a PDF or a spreadsheet so
we've gone over the role the qualities
the tools and the challenges surrounding
a product manager and in this last
section we share with you how you might
fit into this fast-growing in-demand
position I think the way you are
describing a lot of the responsibilities
of a product manager would relate to our
audience pretty closely a lot of the
people that that are on their channel
are either brand strategist or you know
they're strict designers but a lot of
the traits where you're trying to
identify strategy and you know move that
through into a final product or project
I think really relates and touches with
a lot of the people that we are with in
our design community I always prefer to
work more client side than agency side
is that I'd really love having that
longer term you know and so it this is
maybe my my bias here but I always
consider a lot of agency work to be kind
of project to project to project he if
you're our project a project a project
you're working on client a one way you
can client be the next week you don't
actually get a really good sense of who
the customers are who the stakeholders
are what the business truly needs what
the customers truly need he I've never I
haven't seen many product management
like type thing like roles it happened
well in a in a agency world where they
have such a short time frame it is
something that
you know can take some time to just show
value right so it sounds like it's a
it's a long term in-house goal where
you're there on the client side you're
working in a business you're also
working a little bit on the business and
you're there for the long term because
having that longevity will help you
understand where you came from and where
you can go versus something that's a
little bit short-term like on the agency
side it's just opportunity based and you
don't get enough time to really saturate
and synthesize good solutions or
synthesize a good processor way of
working that's going to be very
effective for their business is that
your or another way to think about is
you have more at-bats you know so if
you're you're like a strategist and you
have a great idea for a product and
convince the client to do it and they do
it great and if it works it's awesome if
it doesn't work you probably have
already moved on anyway or so but as a
product many of you get to do that I'll
see what happened go on the next come up
at bat again and then come up a bat
again and you know by the end of if you
kind of do that a couple times you start
to get a much different sense of what's
gonna create value and so yeah it's a I
think it's a thrill it's real you know I
couldn't think of any other job that I'd
want to do that's fantastic
cool well I think that's it I mean I
don't know is there any other like
partying thoughts or things that you
want to share with us before we wrap up
I don't know I think um you know like I
said I think it's a to me it's one of
the most exciting roles out there and so
if this has been helpful you know I I
hope it has and I hope that if you're
interested in product management you
give it a shot more interested in making
money - they make a pretty good feature
oh yeah I was just looking preparing for
this I was doing some googling and I
found that product management is not one
of the is the kind of the top paying
tech job yeah it's a it's a it's a great
career if you're interested in variety
and being resourceful and it's very
challenging it's not for everyone but
you know payoff is there too it's now
it's not one of the top line jobs you
can have so this is specifically for
tech salaries so they've done average
like follow the money right here's like
well in the tech world how much are
people making
so this right here is for data analytics
right now the average is 137 K product
management is a hundred and forty five K
and design is a hundred and twenty seven
K and then software engineering is a
hundred and thirty seven K so it looks
like product management is trending up
and it's above all the other ones where
if we look at and compare the top graph
and the below graph you can see that
software engineering was ahead at some
point and then all of a sudden in two
thousand sixteen and seventeen it
leapfrog the head and now it's above in
terms of averages so it's it's really
interesting to to hear and I know that
this is very specific to the tech market
because I know some of our designer
friends are gonna be looking this like
that I I do not make that as a as a
designer that's that's ridiculous but I
know this is very specific to a
particular market so if you're following
the money if you're in the places where
your skills are needed either as a
designer or product manager or you know
engineer there is opportunity out there
if you're if you're developing the right
skills as Justin has shared with us and
if you're bringing true value to the
businesses that you work with or the the
customers or clients that you work with
if you're solving bigger problems that
have real impact in terms of revenue or
reach like these are things that people
value companies value and they will pay
top dollar and that's why we see these
spikes and median salaries and average
salaries because you know they're people
are really carving a good place for
themselves out in the world so maybe
this is a different conversation that we
have another time and we kind of dig in
deep here but I think this is a nice
note to end on
where people can see this and and see
the trends and make decisions for
themselves or these is this a space that
they want to get into and and what are
the skills that they need to develop so
thank you Justin so much for sharing all
of this information thank you for
sharing your experiences it's very
helpful for me to kind of mindmap your
experiences to my own and kind of
understand the product manager role in a
much clearer way awesome well thank you
very much for having me it's been really
fun all right well we will see you guys
all next time and Justin thank you so
I just want to say thank you to err
table for sponsoring this episode as we
discovered in our conversation today
product managers wear a lot of hats in
their multifaceted fast-paced
environments so they need tools that can
flex and grow with their ever-changing
needs air table is the all-in-one
collaboration platform that keeps up
with even the fastest moving product
teams it can handle any content you
throw at attachments long text notes
checkboxes and so much more you and your
team can ID eight organize and execute
your ambitious product vision in a
single place at a glance you can quickly
see from a high level the progress of
all of your initiatives or you can drill
down to any of these specific details to
understand how to unblock your projects
our future famine credit by signing up
using the link in the description air
table comm slash the future hope you
enjoyed this episode do you have a small
product that you want to ship let us
know by leaving us a comment below
as always don't forget to Like comment
and subscribe because it really helps us
out
we'll see you all in the future